# RYAN BISHOP SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

217-556-3251	<b>EMPLOYER TO-DO</b>
✓ rdbishop06@gmail.com	APPLICATION EVAL.
rdbishop19.github.io	PHONE SCREEN
github.com/rdbishop19	HIRING MGR. INTERVIEW
<u></u>	IN-OFFICE INTERVIEW
in linkedin.com/in/ryandanielbishop	FOLLOW-UP

#### **SKILLS**

- Software:
  - (proficient): Python, JavaScript, React, SQL, HTML, CSS, Git, GitHub, JIRA, AutoHotkey
  - o (familiar): Django
- Data Science:
  - Data-wrangling/data-analysis
  - Supervised machine learning
- Strengths
  - Creativity, critical thinking, problem solving
  - Teamwork, public-speaking, communication
  - Customer support/service
  - Agile, Lean/Six Sigma, project management

# **PROJECTS**

# **DEBUG DOCKET** Front-End Capstone (NSS)

**Debugging** is an important skill for any developer. But bugs can have a bad reputation, being **costly**, **stress-inducing**, and **annoying**. I built **DEBUG DOCKET** to approach software bugs with a growth mindset through *healthy time management*, *helpful analytics* and *team engagement*.

- Single-Page Application built utilizing React
   Hooks with full CRUD-functionality for tracking
   to-do list of bug tickets and auto-tracking time
   spent on each bug
- Automated timer utilizing time management Pomodoro® Technique for consecutive work/break periods with friendly reminders
- Find fellow developer colleagues and view & help with their reported bugs
- github.com/rdbishop19/Debug-Docket

# **2048-game** Python personal project

Before I joined *Nashville Software School*, I was teaching myself Python and **testing my abilities**, so I built this clone of my favorite mobile game.

- nested array manipulation/mathematics
- state comparison
- display and formatting techniques
- directional move event-handlers
- game over/high score functionality
- github.com/rdbishop19/2048-game

# **EDUCATION**

#### NASHVILLE SOFTWARE SCHOOL

Full-stack software development bootcamp | Nashville, TN | Sep 2019 - Mar 2020

#### ILLINOIS COLLEGE

B.S. in Biology & Spanish | Jacksonville, IL | 2006 - 2010 Graduated summa cum laude

#### LITCHFIELD HIGH SCHOOL

Graduated Valedictorian | Litchfield, IL | 2002 - 2006

#### **ABOUT**

I learned about **software development** working previously in a customer-facing technical role in the food production industry. This position introduced me to **Statistical Data Analysis**, **Regression Analysis**, **Machine Learning**, and programming and database management (**Python/SQL**). Leveraging this technical experience and a decade of business experience, I transitioned into professional software development via **Nashville Software School**. I'm a **lifelong learner** and inspired by continuous improvement **principles**, software design **patterns**, and passionate **people**.

## **EXPERIENCE**

## **SOFTWARE DEVELOPER**

Nashville Software School | Nashville, TN | Sep 2019 - Mar 2020

Full-stack 6-month web development program encompassing both individual and group project learning and experience in software design and production.

Tech Stack: Python, Django, SQL, React, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Git, GitHub

#### **Group Projects:**

- Personal dashboard Single-Page Application: 2 separate sprints, built first in Vanilla JavaScript, and again in React, both utilizing JSON-server for persistent data storage. Personally implemented UI/UX affordances for the Chat Messaging and Add a Friend features, and facilitated group-programming for User Authentication.
- Nashville Itinerary Planner application: search restaurants, parks, meetups, and music concerts.
   Championed Eventbrite API for fetching local event data, and also wrote and refactored dynamic functions for displaying results data across all 4 unique API endpoints.
- Celebrity tribute static HTML page: organized repeated group practice of the Git/GitHub workflow with team, as this was our first experience using both platforms.

# FIELD APPLICATION SPECIALIST

Perten Instruments (A Perkin-Elmer Company) | IL, TN | Aug 2013 - Sep 2019

Analytical instrument company providing solutions for food ingredient screening, formulation, process monitoring, and final product quality control.

**Technical Support/Customer Service:** installation, training, and troubleshooting of on-site analytical equipment and software, including near infrared (NIR) and rheology lab instruments, utilized for the functional and compositional analysis of grain, feed, food, flour, and seed products. NIR machines with installed regression models provide a customer solution that is fast, low-cost, and easy-to-use.

**Data Science:** creation of predictive NIR models using machine learning regression analysis with spectroscopy data via third-party and in-house data analysis tool-kits (**Unscrambler, SQL, Python, R**).

- Data-wrangling of customer spectroscopy data sets using Excel & Unscrambler software to match 3rd-party reference chemistry data
- **Regression models** utilizing *supervised machine-learning* (Partial Least Squares Regression and k-nearest neighbors algorithms)
- Installed/updated predictive models on customer equipment to improve accuracy and provide OA/OC process control
- Customer collaboration discussing predictive model & process control improvements
- AutoHotkey scripts automating standardized customer regression reports
- VBA automation scripts improving data analysis & data cleansing workflow
- Phone/remote desktop customer support to troubleshoot database and application issues
- Onsite multi-day **customer training** of analytical equipment and software
- Follow-up customer support/documentation

# **MEDICAL TECHNICIAN**

Memorial Medical Center | Springfield, IL | Nov 2010 - Aug 2013

- Surgical Pathology: assisted Pathologists with preparing and processing surgical specimens and performed diener duties during autopsies
- Administrative: created new documentation to streamline onboarding for new hires